Gould Family (1729-1891) and Gould Homestead (1908-1977) Papers Ms 6
Fairfield Museum and History Center
Gould Family (1729-1891) and Gould Homestead (1908-1977) Papers
1729-1891, 1908-1977
Ms 6
Fairfield Museum and History Center
1.75 Linear feet (4 boxes; 4 oversize items; 1,000 items approx)
Gould family
Gould Foundation (Fairfield, Conn.).
Gould, John, 1801-1871
Conditions Governing Access note
There are no restrictions on access to this collection.
Custodial History note
Items in this collection were donated by Eleanor S. Cathcart, Elbert S. Overbaugh and other unknown donors. Accession numbers L1983.July.1 and L1986.June.6 also make up the collection.
Scope and Contents note
This collection is composed of 4 boxes of documents and account books and 4 oversize items--an account book and three photographs. The bulk of the collection consists of the papers, both personal and business, of Captain John Gould. The personal papers of the Captain range from numerous bills for tailor-made clothes to poetry on small bits of paper. Equally diverse are his business papers, which include not only bills but also insurance and sales contracts for his schooners and a few letters regarding cargoes of the same.
Also in this collection are: (1) some older Gould family papers, chiefly legal documents (which are quite fragile); (2) legal documents, correspondence, reports and newspaper clippings of the Gould Homestead Summer Home for Women (later the Gould Foundation); and (3) photographs of the Gould family members and their residence, the Homestead.
Within the folders, the arrangement is alphabetical according to subject matters where feasible, and within those categories, chronological. Otherwise, chronological order prevails.
Biographical/Historical note
Nathan Gold of St. Edmondsbury, England arrived in the new village of Fairfield in the year 1648, establishing within a short time his preeminence in the community as, among other things, constable, assistant judge of Connecticut's General Assembly, and the commander of Fairfield's militia. His descendents carried on this tradition of civic responsibility: his son, Nathan, Jr. (d. 1723), served as Lieutenant Governor of Connecticut for many years; his great-grandson, Colonel Abraham Gold (1732-1777) was killed fighting the British in Ridgefield, CT; and his last male descendant, Captain John Gould (1801-1871), served as notary public, representative (and later senator) in Connecticut's General Assembly, railroad commissioner, moderator of town meetings and United States Marshall by appointment of President Abraham Lincoln.
Captain John Gould was also a businessman, the owner of a fleet of schooners that over a period of approximately forty years (1826-1865) plied trade between New York City and Richmond, VA and later Liverpool, England. A measure of his success, both as a businessman and as a public official, was the stately mansion known as Gould Homestead which he had built in 1840. This Greek revival home stood at 172 Post Road in Fairfield until 1956, when it was torn down to be replaced by a Food Fair supermarket.
The Gould Homestead was the site of the Gould Homestead Summer Home for Women during the years 1910-1955. The Gould Homestead Summer Home for Women was established under the will of Captain Gould's daughter, Elizabeth Gould (1825-1908) to provide a free vacation home to working women of Fairfield County.
After the demolition of the original Homestead in 1956, the vacation home was run at 85 Post Rd., Fairfield. By 1967 however, the Homestead no longer attracted working women as a vacation home. The trustees of the Gould estate then established a scholarship fund for female residents of Fairfield County, initially under the auspices of the Gould Foundation (1968-1977) and later (1977 to present) under the management of Bridgeport University.
References:
Banks, Elizabeth V. H. This is Fairfield: 1639-1940. New Haven: The Walker-Rackliff Company, 1960.
Cutter, Richard, et al., ed. Genealogical and Family History of the State of Connecticut., Vol. II, pp.757-758. New York: Lewis Historical Publishing Company, 1911.
Hurd, D. Hamilton. History of Fairfield County, Connecticut, with Illustrations and Biographical Sketches of Its Prominent Men and Pioneers. pp. 317-320. Philadelphia: L. W. Lewis and Company, 1881.
Gould, Elizabeth B. (Elizabeth Burr), 1825-1908; Account books--Connecticut--Fairfield.; Correspondence.; Endowments; Houses--Connecticut--Fairfield; Photographs.; Receipts(financial records); Ships
- Box I
  - Bills, contracts, legal documents, miscellaneous, 1729-1823; Folder A; 19 items
    - Contracts for sale of land, 5 items
    - Writs, 2 items
    - Inventory and distribution of estate of Abraham Gold, 1778-1779
    - Account between Hezekiah Gold and Elizabeth Gold, 1777-1783
    - Bills, 2 items
    - Miscellaneous notes, 2 items
  - Captain John Gould bills, personal, Folder B; 20 items
    - Coal
    - Cobbler
    - Doctor, 1826-1844
    - Groceries, 1827-1836
    - Hotel accommodations, 1840-1848
  - Captain John Gould bills, personal, Folder C; 29 items
    - Housewares, 1834-1835
    - Liquor, 1835-1836
    - Postage, 1834, 1841
    - State and town taxes
  - Captain John Gould bills, personal, Folder D; 25 items
    - Tailoring and fabrics, 1834-1845
  - Captain John Gould bills, personal, Folder E; 24 items
    - Tuition, 1832-1844
  - Captain John Gould bills, personal, Folder F; 19 items
    - Wages, 1834-1844
    - Wagon repair, 1835-1838
    - Miscellaneous
  - Captain John Gould bills, business, Folder G; 9 items
    - Allen and Paxson Co., 1832-1844
    - Gilbert Allen and Co., 1830-1832
  - Captain John Gould bills, business, Folder H; 12 items
    - John Pitts, Captain of the Schooner Hornet, 1833-1835
  - Captain John Gould bills, business, Folder I; 14 items
    - John Pitts, Captain of the Schooner Hornet, 1835-1837
  - Captain John Gould bills, business, Folder J; 25 items
    - Doane Sturges and Company, 1833-1837
  - Captain John Gould bills, business, Folder K; 5 items
    - Schermerhorn Willis and Co., 1833-1834
  - Captain John Gould bills for schooners, Folder L; 36 items
    - Courier, n.d.
    - Greenway, 1844-1845
    - Hornet, 1833-1837
  - Captain John Gould bills for Schooner Hornet, Folder M; 22 items
    - Provisions, 1833-1837
    - Sails and sail making, 1833-1836
    - Commissions, procuring, advertising, 1834-1837
    - Harbor Master's fees, 1833, 1837
  - Captain John Gould bills and letter for schooners, Folder N; 27 items
    - Hornet miscellaneous bills, 1833-1837
    - Hornet letter, signature illegible, 1832
    - Lynchburg bills, 1843-1847
  - Captain John Gould letters, legal documents and bills for schooners, Folder O; 25 items
    - Lynchburg letters, 1838-1839; 3 items
    - Richmond bills, 1839-1844
    - Virgina bill, letter and statement of foundering, 1848, 1854, n.d.
    - Contract to build ships, 1836, 1845
    - receipt for payment on ships being built, 1844-1845
  - Captain John Gould schooners' sales and insurance contracts, Folder P; 18 items
    - Contracts for sale of ships, 1831, 1843, 1850
    - Statement of ownership of ships, 1831, 1844
    - Insurance contracts, 1826, 1856-1865
  - Captain John Gould bills of lading, account with Walter Thorp and miscellaneous business letters, Folder Q; 19 items
    - Bills of lading, 1832-1845
    - Letter from Schermerhorn Willis and Co., 1834
    - Letter from R. Hoyt, 1839
    - Letter from James Stubs, 1849
    - Letter from James Piker, 1852
    - Account with Walter Thorp, 1836-1837
    - Bills and account re: Gould's role as administrator of Walter Thorp's estate, 1836-1844
  - Captain John Gould miscellaneous business papers and bills, cancelled checks, Folder R; 63 items
    - Papers re: Gould's role as school commissioner, 1835
    - Papers re: Gould's role as railroad commissioner, 1859
    - Papers re: Gould's role as United States Marshall, 186?
    - Papers re: Gould's role as delegate to state conventions, 1848, 1855
    - Bills paid by Gould for Samuel A. Nichols, 1832, 1838
    - Cancelled checks, 1859-1870
  - Captain John Gould miscellaneous, Folder S; 31 items
    - Poems
    - Receipts, 1835, 1836
    - Promissory notes, 1858, 1866
    - Notes (undated arithmetic figuring)
  - Captain John Gould undated papers found in account books II, III, IV, and V, Folder T; 15 items
  - Bills, contracts, miscellaneous, 1872-1891; Folder U; 18 items
    - Bills, 1872-1886
    - Contract for sale of land, 1885
    - Letters, 1872, 1875, 1888
    - Miscellaneous, 1876-1891
    - Letters to Jeremiah Gould re: cow's death on railroad tracks, 1851-1853
    - Calling cards-E. Gould and Mrs. J. Gould
  - Gould Homestead: Papers relating to Management of Elizabeth R. Gould's trust, Folder V; 18 items
    - Legal documents re: assets of trust, 1914, 1955
    - Minutes of trustees' meetings, 1951-1956
    - Treasurer's report, 1955
    - Correspondence among trustees (see box for full list), 1949-1956
  - Gould Homestead: Documents relating to sites and contents, Folder W; 16 items
    - Legal documents (contracts for sale of property, etc.), 1951-1955
    - Correspondence (see box for full list), 1941-1956
    - Inventory, 1932
  - Gould Homestead: Its management as vacation home, Folder X; 67 items
    - Leaflet, 1910
    - Notes for speech, 1923
    - Receipts of expenses, 1835
    - Autobiography of Katherine M. Spaulding, 1935
    - Letter, list and pamphlet for donation, 1941
    - Thank-you notes from guests, 1951, 1966
    - Monthly reports of expenses, 1955, 1965-1967
    - "The American's Creed" DAR publication
    - "The Gould Homestead: A Memorial" pamphlet
    - Gould Homestead leaflet
    - Note
  - Gould Homestead: Newspaper clippings, Folder Y; 25 items
  - Gould Foundation, Folder Z; 5 items
    - Newspaper clippings, 1968-1977
    - University of Bridgeport report to donors, 1968-1969
- Box II
  - Captain John Gould account books, Folder A; 2 items
    - Mechanics Bank, 1838-1854
    - Schooner Hornet, 1828-1837
  - Captain John Gould account books, Folder B; 2 items
    - Miscellaneous figures, 1822-1854
    - Schooners Lynchburg and Richmond, 1834-1846
  - Books, Folder C; 2 items
    - Julia Gould's friendship book, 1854-1858
    - Gould Homestead reunions, 1941, 1947, 1959
  - Gould Homestead Guestbook, 1910-1914; Folder D
  - Gould Homestead Guestbook, 1914-1919; Folder E
  - Gould Homestead Guestbook, 1919-1923; Folder F
  - Gould Homestead Guestbook, 1941-1966; Folder G
- Box III
  - Gould Homestead record books
    - Minutes of trustees' meetings and annual reports, 1909-1914
    - Minutes of trustees' meetings and annual reports, 1913-1966
  - Loose papers from record books, Folder A; 14 items
  - Gould family photographs, Folder B; 13 items
  - Gould Homestead photographs and negatives, exterior, Folder C; 68 items
  - Gould Homestead photographs, interior, Folder D; 12 items
- Box IV
  - Gould Homestead Photographs, miscellaneous people and pets, Folder A; 45 items
  - Miscellaneous acquisitions, Folder B; 5 items
  - Gould Homestead financial reports, 1946-1951; Folder C; 48 items
  - Gould Homestead financial reports, 1952-1955; Folder D; 36 items
  - Gould Homestead financial reports, 1956-1958; Folder E; 36 items
  - Gould Homestead financial reports, 1959-1963; Folder F; 48
  - Gould Homestead application, Folder G
- Captain John Gould account book V, 1840-1843; Oversize Item A
- Three photographs of Gould Homestead (Map-case drawer)